maybe you already knew this but I didn't
and my AI did I asked my AI Chloe is
there any way to open a URL or a file or
a video from inside inside of wsl2 this
has been one of my biggest complaints
since the dawn of time is that wsl2 is a
virtual machine embedded inside windows
it does have knowledge of Windows it has
knowledge of the file system and it has
some magic that it does so that this
kind of a special VM in that it's got
It's aware of the host OS more more than
VMware would be those of you who know me
know that up until this moment I have
been recommending people install VMware
virtual box or podman onto their Windows
machines in order to get a Linux
experience when they need one and those
of you also know that I've been pro and
con pro and con against WSL for years
I've gone back and forth you can see
video of me saying it was the next Linux
desktop now you then you've seen me like
pulling the rest of my hair out because
it blew up on me and but I'm here to
tell you that after discovering what I
just found and I'm going to show you I
cannot ever ever recommend anybody use
anything but wsl2 on Windows in fact the
only thing that I know for
sure I don't even know this for sure now
my whole universe has been shaken by
this discovery it's very like that not
being able to use a USB stick or a u key
from wsl2 which has been a big you know
you know it's been a reason not use it
because you can't plug in your pass key
or something like that you want to have
a drive or something I mean that has
been annoying before but the biggest
annoyance has been that there hasn't
been the ability to script things that
interact with your host OS at one point
those of you are watching know that I
seriously thought about writing a Damon
that would run some a service that would
run on Windows that would answer the
request over the network the tiny little
Network inside your computer so that
your encapsulated virtual machine
containing WSL could communicate with it
and do simple things like play a video
clip or open a web browser all the
things that people who have a host OS
want to do that's like all the things
they want to write one of the simplest
things is something very basic GH off
login right you want to use the GitHub
tool you want to run the login thing and
you it asks you it says would you like
can I open up a web
browser and now you can with wsl2 until
today you couldn't do that so let me
show you what I mean first of all I'm
going to show you what you can do and
how to make it work in wsl2 so the first
thing is what you're looking at right
now this is a Bare Bones terminal this
is this is the terminal that starts up
it's a command line terminal that starts
up it's really really really basic it's
the one that starts up when you start
WSL so like when you type WSL down here
in the search bar it's the thing that
pops up right it's super simple
obviously we're going to integrate this
with westerm and a bunch of other magic
later but for right now this I just
wanted to show just out of the box that
this works perfectly so the the second
thing of this to know is that there's a
command called open and those of you who
have used Linux or Mac are familiar with
this right so and we're getting into I'm
going to show you how to put the open
tool on there but what it does is it it
tries to figure out what it is you're
trying to open and then it opens it let
me give you the first example I'm going
to open my books website using the open
command from the command line this could
have been in a script or anything I'm
just going to hit enter here oops
enter am I still on it I might have
timed out my VNC connection let me make
sure I'm
here it's not it's not doing it maybe
it's not happy right now one more
time okay there we go so you click enter
and and it you can see that opened up
the web browser on my machine I've got
you know stuff but this is the book
right you know you go to the book you
can read about it here I added a new
book by the way which is probably going
to get changed into terminal about them
but more on that later so um so there
you go so now you can actually use this
and that is really important what
why did it freeze am I Frozen okay so
I'm still going to keep recording here
even though my I think I might be
freezing in twitch so what did that just
do that opened a thing now let's let's
try this again with something else let's
just open this readme file right what
does it do it opens the
associated editor in this case I have
got um I have got vs code installed so
it Associated the text file with vs code
and so it opened that up right now
here's here's another crazy thing um I
actually think let me go ahead and close
this one
out I mean it looks like it's it's got a
little bit let's I'm just curious to see
if it'll actually do code code code is a
native Windows command that opens the vs
code editor I I haven't tried this yet I
don't know if it's going to work but I
really want to see if it will okay so it
says the host was not found in the list
of host do you want to allow it anyway
I'm going to say yes
allow oh my God go yes I trust the
authors so what that means is that vs
code has just opened from
wsl2 the the takeaway from this is very
simple the vs the wsl2
integration with the native Windows
system is now complete so you can
interact with applications and open them
in any way that you care to really
including playing sound files and stuff
which haven't tried I'm sure that'll
work just fine by doing this by by doing
this this sort of thing so to those of
you who are like who like to have your
own dot files and your own scripts that
play video clips or they pull up your
favorite website or more importantly let
me show you this one this is a really
important one in fact I'm going to just
try to do it right in front of you sudu
apt install w3m w3m Andor links you know
text based browsing one of the best
advantages of a text based browsing
situation is that you can browse at the
speed of the terminal to get to what you
want to get to and then when you get to
the thing you want if it's got some
graphics or JavaScript capability in it
you tap the comma key and it opens the
graphic browser because you need that to
see that has not worked in wsl2 until
now until now you can do it so so let me
try it so WS w3m so I should be able to
just browse let's go to
[Music]
github.io RBX Rob I think you have to
have htps in there maybe not okay so
here we are we're on the
site and let's just pretend I want to
open this site in my graphic browser
let's try it with a
comma will it work or not it doesn't
look like it's opening it in the browser
I think I'm have to remap it
actually oh it did it did it it did it
in in Windows in w3m it's it's capital M
to open up to open up the page in a
graphic browser and as you saw it just
worked it just worked this is huge
because let me try let me show you this
again so you can I want you to process
what this means so this means with w3m
with no custom configuration at all I
can use a text based browser and go the
speed terminal velocity I can work at
terminal velocity until I get to the
page that I want to see and then when I
want to see the page graphically I can
do in this case the default is shift
capital M so I actually have that map to
comma because that's what lyx uses and
as you can see it opens up your web
browser right away this this is
phenomenally huge for per people that
want to work at terminal velocity this
means you can do t-mo this means that
when you're like editing a file so like
this is another thing let's try this so
like let's install Vim sud do apt
install VI we could do Neo or Vim it
doesn't matter so let me let me show you
L people don't know about this right so
so you know you'll be editing a file and
let's put a URL in here htps
as as github.com rwx Rob whatever all
right so there is the URL right A lot of
people don't know that out of the box
Vim supports GX so GX will will open any
URL that you are within with the graphic
browser so we'll do
GX is it going to work oh my gosh it
works it works it just opened the
browser while from my Vim session I
opened my browser to read the URL while
I was editing the
file I
mean that is so stinking cool that I
mean for there's a few people out there
that just that their jws just dropped to
the ground because you have never been
able to do this in wsl2 before you've
never been able to you've always been
relegated to copying and pasting the URL
and then uh putting it back on there and
and then you know go into the thing and
you've been saying I don't want to use a
terminal I got to go copy and paste the
URL to get my Graphics browser to open
up not anymore not anymore you can just
you can just integrate it directly with
wsl2 this is huge this is 100% Linux on
windows with the least amount of
overhead because it's using wsl2 versus
a VM that you install it is a VM it's
just a VM optimized for Windows that has
permanent permanent
integration with your host system for
everything that means that all of your
file type associations are already known
about if you open Sound if you open a
movie you want to make that cool little
clip clip player automatically it will
do it somebody did say that it could do
it somebody did say in YouTube they're
claiming that they told me this they did
say it could do it and I was like so I
asked my AI today I was like okay let's
see if this is true I pulled up wsl2 to
see if it could be done and it couldn't
be done and then I asked my AI I said
hey can this be done and they said yes
but this is what you have to install and
this is what nobody has told me so far
so I'm going to tell you so you know
it's pretty easy but the first thing you
have to do is you have to sudu apt in up
apt update of course I'm going to do it
anyway just so you can have the steps
sudu appt upgrade update sudu apt um
sudu appt install and then we'll go
ahead and we'll install um
xdg utils so this is what has open in it
right it's the same one that's used on
Linux Linux desktops it's exactly the
same software which is really great for
me because all of my documentation about
how to do things is a lot simpler now
because everything that I document for
Linux is directly the same now for
Windows which blows my mind a little bit
it does it really blows my mind so so
now the next thing to do is um you have
to install something called WSL U sudu
apt install
WSL University apparently something like
I don't know um and then oops I got to
type
correctly install wlu all right so it's
already there and then as soon as you
have those things on there you can
create a file and you can test it just
the way we have already in the video um
let's see try edit oh by the way the
first time you do it it asks permiss
permission it asks you for permission
hey this program wants to do such and
such to WSU dollar and I think it's
trying to mount the file system and you
have to say yes you have to Grant
permission I forgot about that step so
make sure you do that um but but other
than that everything is fine and that's
really it for this video um uh that's
just those two packages that is it that
is all you need to install and it after
that it works and you know I I'm so
blown away by this and my apologies
anybody who's tried to tell me I could
do this the whole time I don't know how
long WSL U has been a thing I do not
know how long WSL has been a thing I I
do not know it could have been around
since the dawn of time and I didn't know
I've been streaming for four years and
at least a year and a half of that ice
stream with WSL on Windows and nobody
told me about this they did see my wsl2
melt completely and caus my computer
span to go through the roof so I'm a
little scared wsl2 I'll tell you that
right now I'm still scared of wsl2
VMware has never done that to me but
with VMware now in the clutches of
broadcom and with VMware unable to
integrate directly the way I just showed
you with the whole system the clear
decision for most people going with
Windows I would think would be to use
wsl2 people have been telling me use
wsl2 all this time and I've been pushing
back for the last 3 weeks saying no it's
going to blow up on everybody you can't
use your USB device and you can't open
anything it has no integration and that
last point the main point that you don't
have system integration to open up files
and stuff is now gone so the other one I
want to show you is the GH off login I'm
not going to do it but make sure you try
this when you do GH off login it
actually opens your browser and it
authenticates and it keeps going on for
you which for me is great because now
the beginners don't have that extra step
of like you know you still have to cut
and paste the number but you don't you
don't have to go open the browser by
yourself it'll actually open it for you
so it does it it queries the internal
file type associations looks and it
transfers them over and it it tells your
host system what kind of file is being
opened so that means it knows about
opening URLs it knows about opening
sound files it knows about opening any
type of file so as long as your host
systems default you know applications
have been set accordingly it'll open it
up which is pretty damn cool in fact I'm
kind of tempted to try other things like
like my zift file right like so I might
be able to to manage like my zift file
my zift my game configurations or or My
you know my pandoc you know books or my
PDF viewer there's one right one of the
things I haven't been able to do I I
generate PDFs all the time writing books
right I've been writing these books I've
been generating PDFs on
WSL um and I've been they have a USB
connect now they have what is that you
may also use USB devices just not
seamless as BMW okay so so apparently
there is also also a USB thing I'll do a
separate video on that but the decision
is very clear here use
wsl2 even with the risk and I admit it's
a small risk even with the risk of it
screwing up your system uh and blowing
up which it has done on me twice uh in
fact people took bets to say how long it
would last before I was anti- WSL
because they knew it would eventually
blow up but if you're a beginner I mean
to install you know how hard it was for
me to install WSL I started a command
terminal and I tped
WSL space-- install and it installed by
itself it installed by itself and it
prompted me it said what username would
you like to use and what password you
like to use and then it said you need to
reboot I rebooted and it it put wsl2
downloaded a bunch you got it all set up
and dropped me right into the terminal
that was it that was it my friends so
short of UND sort of setting up was term
to use wsl2 which I am now going to do
for the default. template repo that I've
been putting in the book this also means
obviously that several hours of the
beginner boost that we did for the
holiday boost are now related you know
gone because we're going to we're going
to replace git bash on windows with wsl2
there is no mist there is no sigin there
is no G bash there is no bware there is
no pod man there is only one true
desktop Linux for Windows in my mind as
of this moment and that is wsl2 and you
know I I have been actively uh aware of
my you know frustrating need to change
my mind when I come into new information
and I have that information confirmed
for me and this information is now
overwhelming that this this is very very
easy for most beginners what is even
more important than that and and I've
always known this is that wsl2 is the
officially supported Microsoft way to
run Linux on Windows so if you if you're
down with using wigit because that's the
new official package manager for Windows
then why would you not be down with
using the official Linux way to put
Linux on
Windows um why is that important if you
are running a school district or if
you're running a coding club or you're
running any of those things the the
amount of friction you're going to get
by using wsl2 on a Windows system is
almost nothing other than knowing how to
set up hypervisors and making sure that
setup which you know is a little bit of
extra setup but not that much um you
know it's not going to be hard it's not
going to be hard to convince people in
it even in a public school system to use
wso2 because that's what Microsoft
supports and the one thing that decision
makers and it care about who are
overworked and underpaid is is Microsoft
going to support it and you might not
like Microsoft especially if they
supporting a Linux distribution but if
you're a decision maker in one of these
organizations and you want the least
amount of friction and the least amount
of extra work to come around using wsl2
might very well be the answer I I do
think get bash is pretty damn close but
for by putting wsl2 on there you get
everything you just saw me use w3m you
cannot install w3m on Windows period it
doesn't exist you can't install it on
Windows the only way to get w3m for text
based browsing the only way to get t-u
people the only way to get t-u at all on
Windows is to install Linux or in some
fashion which means you either install
the old school Boomer sigin the new
school msys 2 which is basically sigwin
for Millennials or you install WSL 2 and
you get all that stuff for free because
it is Linux in every other way it's
exactly like Linux that means all your
package management is good you know if
you sell m 2 you have to learn Pac-Man
for God's sakes why would you do that
when you could install M wl2 and have
opt you could use actually app Rep same
thing you're going to do if you had a
container or some other thing it is a
no-brainer and to all of you are going
to say in the comments I told you so
please say I told you so please say it I
love it when you say I told you so
because so when you say you know when
you start to tell me things like hey I
tried to tell you that you know when you
do say these things it's not like I
ignore you I hear you but I need to get
fully full confirmation
and in this case my AI confirmed it she
goes oh yeah you can do that here let me
show you and she gave me three commands
that need or two commands necessary to
get it to work and I immediately try
them and it worked and I pretty much
blew up on IRC which by the way I invite
you to come in I am now in IRC all day
pretty much in twitch IRC so it's
basically if you don't know how to use
IRC learn how to use it learn how to use
it with twitch come join us um I am in
there all day every day while I'm
working I am sitting in there in the IRC
chat even though I'm not streaming as I
am today um so please come join us in
the IRC we'd love to have you um and no
I'm not going to have a Libra or
whatever because IRC is already
available on Twitch and I know it's not
the real IRC I don't care it's the
accounts are validated they've already
been pre-filtered and that is the only
IRC I'm going to be using for now um so
you know you can save the comment on
that one uh once wso breaks again you
will come back to get bash I very I very
much might
now you can play it Rob it's a uni
system I actually can play it's a unique
system the first time I can play one of
my clips from Windows and say it's a uni
system I am so doing that I am so doing
that I'm just responding so some chats
here maybe I'll keep that in the video
let me read some of the comments from
YouTube uh so YouTuber says yeah I told
you yeah okay uh could you technically
SO2 for the initial set of process and
then run your home free teaching code
absolutely that's exactly what we're
doing Tony Anthony that's exactly what
we're doing open Windows Explorer and
look for Linux node you will see a
mounted file system for
each um let's see what does it say
you'll see amount of file system for
each dist you have installed in WSL nice
uh I did not have to install anything to
get wsl2 for Windows integration it just
worked uh you're talking about file
system integration you're talking about
file system integration right no I um
you can't you can't do the open command
without it in fact I have it in my
terminal
um let me show you okay some somebody is
suggesting that it just worked out of
the box and I didn't have to install
those things and that is factually
incorrect um and I'm going to tell you
what I had to do to make it work so when
I first ran xtg open I ran the open
command and um God it's look at this
already hanging it's already hanging on
me I cannot even get the terminal to
display please tell me it's not going to
hang more yeah watch this happen while
I'm making the video this is this is
just user error I'm running VNC guys
this is that's the problem here the
problem here is that I'm running VNC and
it probably timed out so let me do W
cell again and by the way you when when
you can eventually have it so when you
type bash it'll type it'll be you know
it'll pull up a West term or whatever so
I had to open a new one looks like might
time my other one out um what I'm trying
to tell you is that when I did open the
first time it it listed all the things
that it tried to open which is really
cool including w3m and links and
everything and it failed because it none
of those things could open the thing in
question and when I put um then when I
installed WSL on uh it was able to open
everything without a problem and it just
it just prompted me uh for that and it
went from there so I I don't know if
there's something else I'm missing there
but I'm just telling you my experience
so um for your next trick use the WSL to
install additional and Alternate Linux
dist in WS2 yeah I've done that many
many times back in my WSL 2 days I had a
whole bunch of different lenux dros and
I was running them switching between
them and all of that and and that's cool
and all but um because they're separate
VMS and you can even have them run at
the same time if you have a memory um
I'm not interested in that and if you're
a beginner if you're a beginner I
suggest you just stick with the Ubuntu
image and and do WSL install with a
default Ubuntu image I I would not not
suggest pushing WSLS uh too much at this
point uh especially given my experience
with it blowing up on me uh twice so
what I would I'm kind of scared about
even recommending wsl2 at this moment
because as soon as I do it's gonna
something's going to go wrong right um
but so far so good so and you know the
benefits clearly outweigh the negatives
at this time so so so you know people
are suggesting like trying all the
different distri maybe yeah maybe you
should do that but but not yet right so
right now just just get a stable get a
stable Unix uh system on your Windows
machine or in this case Linux system um
and then uh you can always okay yes side
by side yes Jo feeling is exactly what
Microsoft was aiming for in developing
wl2 yes I know it was I know that this
is what Microsoft was going for and and
there are there's literally video
evidence of me I'm going to put it in
the chat if you go search my videos you
will see me you know hoop hoop Haring
WSL when I first got it to work and I
was working I mean not just when I first
got to work when I got to to do some of
these other things I wanted to do two
and three years ago and then everything
went sour so I'm scared I'm I'm not
going to lie I'm scared it blew up so I
know that the micros okay so the
statement from a commenter in YouTube is
that Microsoft this is exactly the
Elation that they're going for and I
know that the team wants this and I have
wanted to back that team up ever since
the beginning I if there's one thing I
want to see succeed over a at at
Microsoft it's the Linux team we want to
see the Linux team at Microsoft win we
want to see them get adopted we want to
see them have a lot of success and it
brought great pain to me to have to say
you know WSL is not the Linux Dro of
2022 like I said it was the desktop drro
you know the biggest Linux drro of all
time you know of 2022 which is what I
said and it turned out that it blew up
on me right after that and I was mad I
was mad at myself I was mad at at
Microsoft and I it wasn't anger at the
team I wanted to support the team I
really did but I you know I was I was
totally made a fool of because I trusted
it and I'm a little worried right now
that by trusting it again and having you
trust it and rewriting my book so that
everybody who reads my book trusts
it is going to have this so if Microsoft
if you're watching this there's a lot on
the line here for me now I know you
don't care you're a big ass company you
know who who cares about this little
YouTuber old man Boomer and and his book
and the kids he's trying to help but I'm
telling you right now don't disappoint
me I'm speaking to you Microsoft please
please don't disappoint me and like well
you have to you're running it on an old
system you're going to have to upgrade
Windows you're going to have to run a
new windows if you're going to do this
you got to run the latest windows we
can't promise wl2 is going to work on
the windows that you're running which is
hell I don't even know what it is
because my Hardware won't even run your
new Windows
Microsoft I'm scared I'm not going to
lie I'm scared because they they could
have they could just pull WSL support
and say sorry your computer is no longer
supported you need to buy a new computer
in order to run Windows and if that
happens I'll go back to my other
position was if you want to do terminal
velocity put Linux on your windows
hardware and kick windows out of
there I still think that's better look
I've said a lot of of bad things about
Linux desktop in the last year and a
half I still think it's better than
Windows with
WSL I I still think it's better than
Windows with WL the only reason in
termal velocity the book that I'm the
other book I'm writing my number one
recommendation to people who have a
Windows machine an Intel machine is
going to be install Linux desktop the
end if you have that option if you don't
have the option the next best option is
wsl2 and by don't have the option if you
want to play your video game and you
also want to become a code Mage right W2
is the option for you it really is it's
the option for you and you know if that
doesn't work and we could always use
VMware the problem with VMware is you
lose all the tight integration it's not
there at all you can use your USB sticks
stuff but you don't get the the tight
integration all right so what I'm like
reading some more
here uh let's see get bash is great but
if you have to Le leave it alone it's
just just use it for get monkey with it
yeah you're talking about dock type
integration yes where casear dev2 is
everything get bash for bash and westerm
best case scenario westerm opens in W2
that's what it will do so by the end of
the night tonight uh my DOT files
configuration as as well as my westerm
configuration and my DOT template
configuration that I talked about
already in the holiday B boost uh will
now open up WSL ch's bash instead
instead of get bash now I could write
some code in there that detects which
one you have I might attempt that I
might attempt that that's the really
great thing about Wes term is it's it's
WR the configuration is written in Lua
so I can actually detect which bash you
have I can progressively enhance and I
can say look if I if you have you know
wsl2 installed will run that bash when
you start up your Wes term otherwise
when you start up westerm will start up
whatever other bash you have maybe the
bash and program files so and and that's
honest to God that's probably the right
way to go with the westerm configuration
that I'm writing um because I mean I I
still want people to have the option of
putting GI bash on there if they don't
want to use wsl2 and that that way they
can pick which one they want and either
of them will work with westerm which I
still recommend everybody get it just it
completely drops Windows terminal
preview in terms of performance and
flexibility and configuration so I'm
still really solidly behind westerm
doing all of this so that that change of
those configuration files will will
happen um and I will obviously I'll have
to redo uh the holiday boost uh videos
about that the the video boo series The
Holiday boost series by the way is one
big long playlist right now you just had
have to work through it and watch the
whole thing um I will eventually make
segmented pieces uh of videos that go
with the book they will not be
considered holiday boost material they
will be
you know Co coexisting I suppose videos
that go with the book and my plan is to
have a permanent playlist that is
directly referenced in the book and the
book directly references the videos and
so the videos directly reference the
book and so you have simultaneously you
have a video that goes with that section
of the book at all times and then that
playlist will be constantly in sync so
those of you who are looking for a
specific video on a specific topic that
is coming it's just I have to finish the
book first and and then we'll do that so
rather than not make a series at all I
went ahead and did the holiday boost but
just like every other boost we've ever
done stuff changes in the middle and
that has happened to me since 2013 in
2013 when I started skill stack every
single time we go down a path something
new comes out or something new happens
and we have to adapt we have to adapt
and we have to change and we have to
assess whether it's going to work or not
sometimes we have to change our mind
back to the original thing but that's
been a natural part of this whole
boosted mentoring kind of idea since I
started skill stack so I can't I can't
promise you things aren't going to
change again it's just it's always been
that way um so so let's see and then
when you get back to the worst case
scenario you could argue familiarity
with Linux commands later on yes um
sometimes I install another Dr simply
because I temporary screwed up your main
one yeah yeah I'm running W 2 on 2010
vintage machine nice uh Windows terminal
is really great but cross plop from
westerm is even better that's good to
hear you say that because I know that uh
you know you you've been really you know
watching that whole space and it's good
to I I've I'm a newbie at westerm I've
used westerm only for one week and I I
have never used a better terminal in my
life it it is it is so amazing and and
I'm continuing to to to pursue that the
the conf the the the Lua configuration
is just so great for an educ like me
because I can make a single terminal
configuration that works on any
operating system at all and it it finds
what to run and it runs the best thing
it does the best possible thing it could
do that's not possible with aaker withl
or anything that has terminal based
configuration in fact I am such a fan of
of executable configuration of you know
U of that now in Lua whether it be neam
or Lua that when when something when I
come across a new application who
configuration follows Lua I'm
immediately impressed and I'm like yes
yes more please yes more of that please
more please last time I searched for
Windows terminal Alternatives it didn't
exist I know it's because it's just it's
constantly evolving right this is why
this is why I haven't made a book in the
past I have to go rewrite these sections
of the book because something new is
coming up so you know I call this book I
call it Perpetual publishing because
these books that I'm publishing you know
when I finally get to a point like for
like 2 seconds where I can publish a
printed version and put it on Amazon
it'll immediately be out of date and
this is why I don't do books I have been
an educator and a and and interested in
helping other people learn for more than
20 years and I've always hated books why
because they always get out of date and
then you have to fight with teaching
people the new things and you have to
constantly so unless you have a
Perpetual publishing model which I've
currently kind of invented for myself
then there's no way to keep up there's
no way to keep up what term is hot
reloading your config oh my God isn't it
amazing El laity you had to activate hot
reloading your config but now westerm
does it automatically out of the box
which is just so crazy awesome um so
yeah there are some issues with both WSL
and that got that got bash got me
through like I said it didn't work for
me having WSL installed I had it screwed
up with your bash uh I mean it it well
well we're going to hit them we're going
to hit those right so can you install
Vell via westerm yes you can you
absolutely can I terminal is doing is
just getting you what you're using there
right so you can you can do it from pow
shell or whatever right but um we're
actually going to go through the steps
to install West term after I write them
in the book um if you want to sit around
I mean this video is kind of long now
but if you want to sit around with me
while I figure this out and I rewrite
the book please join us on the live
stream and and you can watch me do that
uh to those of you who have struggled I
mean yesterday yesterday's boost at the
end of it was was some of problem atic
because we had a lot of people who had
tried to do some of the extra stuff in
their terminal right and they had kind
of shot themselves in the foot because
it was just G bash and it didn't have
the other things and their werm wasn't
wasn't doing what they expected and that
is largely going to go away now because
it's just going to be install
wsl2 activate the command line opening
things that we did install those two
things um and uh in fact you know that
actually it's not even that it's just do
that and open up the GH
tool what I want to know is where are we
going to write the West term we have to
figure out where to what where to write
the West term configuration in git bash
so that we can open a terminal um from
there but but I I'm pretty sure we'll
figure that out and it's not that hard
because one thing I do know is that WSL
2's file system mounts are on are access
I mean the host system Mount file system
is accessible to to the the wsl2 system
that's that's been since the beginning
of WSL 2 WSL one had kind of an
emulation layer the only problem westerm
doesn't play nice with opacity if it's
not the main program uh that has GPU
control so you can't maximize the video
in westerm with
opacity uh let's see the only problem
westerm doesn't play nice with opacity
if it's not the main program that has
GPU control
oh wow that's interesting because it's
it's used to being a GPU thing
right well it will be the main program
it's not like we're running it under
WSL there's a good of issue on
it I I don't think that's going to be a
problem but I'm not prepared to say that
yet so stay tuned wso has already
installed in Wind 11 by default really
does it have a buntu in it
already I didn't know that I haven't got
window I mean I knew windows did a lot
of that but I wasn't sure nobody pays
for Windows anymore at least someone
pays for
Windows uh one of my gripes ISS that
ghosty is their config especially since
they aren't official docs yet if they if
ghosty doesn't have Lu config I don't
want to even look at it I'm not I'm not
at all interested at all I I'm not I I'm
not it's such a no-brainer to have Lu
can pig now in fact I am seriously
thinking about adding Lua configuration
into Bonsai as as a subm module because
having having default Lua configuration
integrated into Bonsai for to create any
Bonsai Branch any Bonsai command branch
that you made having it have automatic
Lua configuration built in have a
persistence driver that uses Lua oh my
Lord that would be so awesome uh has a
lot of security P it having a having a
programming language as a configuration
file does have security flaws for sure
but not if you have control of the
program right not not if you have
control of the configuration file it's
no it's no less secure than SSH using an
SSH config file it's not because you
have
control if if somebody else were passing
in the configuration or if you're
querying some external Source tainted
Source first up in the configuration
yeah but don't do
that other dist needs to be installed W
install install to yeah WSL space D-
install installs a buntu and that's what
I wanted to do for beginners I want
beginners to have a buntu server that
that is the hands down the vanilla
standard in
servers uh Lin hold arbitrary scripts
yes yes it
can uh let's see it's not a programming
problem it's a quality of life problem
like sometimes the stream well if I'll
tell you this one of the reasons to use
westerm is for all that fast GPU color
support and if it turns out that wsl2
stops westerm from being as impressive
that's definitely a consideration
um par is looking at L yeah yes it kind
of is uh let's see what else we got
um how a terminal emulator is important
uh they're all the same they are
absolutely not the same and um if you
don't realize the difference you
definitely will um if you're just
looking at a terminal that's fine if you
I'm telling you when you spend 15 hours
in front of a terminal and you've
integrated color things in your terminal
and you're doing a lot of like nbim
popup completion stuff like that that
little lag time because you don't have
GPU acceleration becomes extremely
noticeable but it takes somebody who
codes 15 hours a day to know so a lot of
people that are new to this are not
going to understand the difference and I
promise you you talk to any veterans
they they will tell you the one of the
reasons I got a Mac the very first
reasons I got a Mac a long time ago was
because because I am spending 12 to 15
hours staring at a computer at day and
the the I know it doesn't seem like it
but when you spend that much time the
the ergonomics of looking at a screen
that has the crispest resolution
possible actually matters it makes your
eyes have less eye strain you guys think
I'm it's like sit in front just to get a
sense of this sit in front of a screen
that's just white it's got black text on
white and stare at that for 6 hours and
then you tell me if you don't want to
change it because the Aesthetics of what
you're doing and what you're staring at
all day matter if that's what you're
doing if you're a knowledge Warrior and
you're doing it all day every day and
your job is staring at this thing it
does matter even a tiny little Advantage
like a 4K screen when there was no 4K
screens before which Mac had before
anybody else or you know a GPU
accelerated westerm screen or the
absolutely crystal clear Cris this is
not westerm but the really you know
clear crisp fonts that exist when you're
using the nerd font on a bunch of nerd
font on on on westerm it's just
absolutely overwhelmingly different and
you know I compare God just just looking
at the same stuff you go back to my
other videos from before even from four
three four years ago and you're looking
at me using a really GPU accelerated
alacrity or gnome terminal and you
compare to Wester even today and you can
totally see the difference and it's you
know so so is it necessary probably not
you know and I I'm I'm listening to
Dennis Dennis is probably I mean last
miles you know he works on his black and
white sonest you know and you know he's
he's like you're full of it right and
and that's fine but I I'm you know it's
2024 and there are modern Terminals and
I think you should definitely look at
them um I I still think Mac OS is better
than than Windows with with wsl2 buy a
landslide buy a landslide I think buying
a Mac machine and BSD uh Mac machine for
development is
overwhelmingly better than a Windows
machine with wsl2
overwhelmingly I still think it's an
overwhelming difference over even a $200
laptop running running you know or even
a$1 thousand laptop running running
Linux on the desktop I there's no
comparison to me between a Mac and and
that and there's going a lot of people
are going to disagree and they're going
to say you're just a sh for apple and
stuff that's fine you do you if that's
what you think you can say that but I my
experience is that it's been absolutely
different and not to mention the fact
that my work literally issued Max
officially to us for work and that was
it so yeah uh I am going to do the
proxmox biix actually um I'm going to do
a a whole proxmox video uh I don't know
if it's going to be tonight or tomorrow
but I'm going to rebuild kubernetes on
my proxmox machine uh there is Chris
there is an entire video there's a
12-hour
video um I don't know where it is but
there is a 12-hour video of me setting
prox MOX up and going through all the
home labin specs so and there is a book
coming there is a book coming home lab
init it's called Linux home lab init and
it is that book if I start writing stuff
in there that's where I'll put those
specs for you because that that book is
going to be entirely about setting up a
proxmox home server for your home lab uh
on YouTube yep I don't remember the one
you might have to search it's really
hard to find stuff um between there and
skill stack you might find it but
uh especially for devs too bad it's not
cheap yeah they're not cheap I'm not I'm
not saying that right yes you can
install Linux on anything yeah
installing Linux on a Mac would just be
I've done it I my first Linux was
installed on a power PC in
six yeah that's that's a true story I
was teral onlyon baby yeah he couldn't
run any graphics there was no support
for any graphics drivers at
all it was that was tough I I was using
mut for on my email and IRC for all my
communications and links for all my web
browsing I had no
Graphics I took over the family home
computer and I booted this thing on
there I gave up Need for Speed I had a I
had a steering wheel and everything I
gave it all up I gave it all up people
tell me like oh you're an apple shill
and how could you possibly call yourself
a link person I'm like I threw a
$150 race you know set
thrustmaster and all my favorite video
games and the entire family's home
computer accessibility to a graphics
desktop on our Mac power PC while I had
young children in the garbage so that I
could run Linux in the terminal only
like an OG boss I don't want to hear
your about not knowing
Linux probably time for me to stop
making this video I'm going to push stop
on the video now